<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance to vindicate His Excellence Robert Earle of Essex from some false aspersions cast upon his proceedings. To the 17. of August. 1643</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91643</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E71_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859764</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91643)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 12:E71[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance to vindicate His Excellence Robert Earle of Essex from some false aspersions cast upon his proceedings. To the 17. of August. 1643</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct: 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1591-1646 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111861:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111861:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE <hi>TO VINDICATE</hi> HIS EXCELLENCE ROBERT EARLE OF ESSEX From ſome falſe Aſperſions caſt upon His PROCEEDINGS.</p>
            <p>To the 17. of Auguſt. 1643.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>T. W.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="remonstrance">
            <pb facs="tcp:111861:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111861:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE raſh and injurious ſpeeches, which ſome miſunderſtanding peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have let fall concerning the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of our noble <hi>Generall</hi> have drawne from us, with no leſſe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice than neceſſity, this ſhort and true vindication. Though his <hi>Excellence,</hi> ſecure in his owne worth and conſcience, would forgive ſuch calumnies, and that in the nobleſt way of forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to take no notice at all of them: yet wee who are privy to all paſſages, whom it concernes in Juſtice to ſatisfie the world, and whom it more behooves to vindicate than it can doe any man to calumniate, cannot be guilty of ſo great a neglect, as not endeavouring to make the truth appeare. And ſince it is proved by frequent experience, that the grounds of all jealouſies and ſuſpitions, which people ignorant of the preſent actions are apt to conceive againſt any man, are uſually raiſed from ſome precedent demeanours of the ſame perſon: let it not be thought amiſſe, if wee digreſſe a little from the preſent narration, in ſhewing what his <hi>Excellence</hi> has formerly beene, and how little cauſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111861:3"/>can ariſe from thence for any man to ſuſpect his truth, valour, or diſcretion. It will not be denyed that my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> was eſteemed as loyall a ſervant to the Royall Family, as true a Patriot to all intereſts of <hi>England,</hi> and as conſtant an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer in the maintenance of the reformed Religion (and it has pleaſed God to put <hi>England</hi> of late years into that condition, that the greateſt advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her temporall intereſt is by protection of the reformed Religion) as any Nobleman whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, as by his former free ſervices for the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, Holland, &amp;c.</hi> may plainly appeare; in which not onely his Majeſty but the Queene of <hi>Bohemia</hi> will be pleaſed to acknowledge his fidelity, ready alwayes, though never obliged by the Court, nor waiting upon his Majeſty in that way, to ſerve him truly in all warlike and honourable employments; and in the late buſineſſes of <hi>Cales</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> though he commanded not in chiefe, and little was done; yet what was beſt done, was done by him, as the wiſeſt which were there will acknowledge. So that it may ſeeme his Majeſty made choice of his ſervice as a man of unqueſtionable fidelity to his Country; and the repreſentative body of the Kingdome now choſe him as a man of undoubted loyalty to his Soveraign; thoſe two vertues being
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111861:3"/>inſeparable in the breaſt of a noble <hi>Engliſhman;</hi> &amp; which his <hi>Excellence</hi> profeſſes that in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he beleeves this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to disjoyne. Upon this the Parliament in this extreme and ſad neceſſity choſe him their <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> with a Commiſſion as large and abſolute as ever was granted; it being conceived that a more narrow Commiſſion was not worthy to engage him in ſo dangerous an enterpriſe, nor of power ſufficient to enable him to the accompliſhment of great deſignes. Which was the practice (to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with elder times) of that ſoveraigne Senate of <hi>Rome;</hi> who in times of moſt imminent danger, waving her uſuall government in warre by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, choſe a Dictator, putting the ſole and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent command of the Souldiery upon one man for a limited time; it being obſerved by wiſeſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that too ſtrait a limitation of <hi>Generals</hi> in their power has been deſtructive to their beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes; for which not only the old petty States of <hi>Greece</hi> have been blamed, but great <hi>Carthage</hi> which was able to conteſt with <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf, and in later times the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (as wiſe as they think their Councels) have loſt much by it. Therfore in a plain narration we ſhall endeavour to ſhew that his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence has not been wanting in any performance,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111861:4"/>unleſſe diſobedience to his power, want of neceſſary pay for his Souldiers, or too frequent interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of another power have ſometimes hindred his real intentions. At our march from <hi>Windſor</hi> (where the neceſſity of the ſeaſon, and the ſafeguard of the City had long detained the body of our Army) the Souldiers were much in arrere, which was willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forborn till the State ſhould be better able, upon promiſe of conſtant pay for the future. We came to <hi>Reading,</hi> lay 16. dayes before it; no mony came; upon the Treaty his <hi>Excellence</hi> ſent the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who liked it, and the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to forbear plundring were promiſed 12. ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a man, beſides their pay, but their pay could not be had, although his <hi>Excellence</hi> after 8. dayes expectation made a journey himſelf to <hi>London</hi> for it; in the mean time, by reaſon of that infected town a great ſicknes and mortality fell upon the Army; notwithſtanding his <hi>Excellence</hi> by the advice of his Councell of War, intended to march thence for better ayre; but ſuch a generall mutiny was raiſed for want of mony, that his <hi>Excellence,</hi> though with much courage, &amp; juſt ſeverity, he began to ſuppreſs it, was adviſed by his Councel of War to deſiſt for fear of a generall defection, till mony might come from the City. Notwithſtanding upon this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111861:4"/>his <hi>Excellence</hi> removing to <hi>Cawſham</hi> houſe (which he did to prevent the infection) many of them did disband and go away. The day following his <hi>Excellence</hi> comming thither received intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the defeat of the <hi>Devon</hi> forces under the command of the Earle of <hi>Stanford,</hi> at <hi>Stretton</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and that P. <hi>Maurice</hi> and Marquis <hi>Harford</hi> were deſigned that way. Whereupon he ſent an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe with order to Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> forthwith to march with his forces to joyn with the forces of <hi>Devon,</hi> and the other Weſtern Countries to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the joyning of the enemies forces; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all writ to the Governor of <hi>Briſtol</hi> to aſſiſt Sir <hi>W. Waller</hi> with ſuch horſe and foot as he could conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently ſpare out of his garriſon. And that nothing might be wanting for the ſafety of the Weſtern Country, which any way lay in his <hi>Excellences</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, (well knowing them to be of greateſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) at a Councell of War it was fully debated, put to the queſtion, and reſolved that a ſtrong par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of horſe and foot ſhould then be ſent after P. <hi>Maurice</hi> to fall upon him before he ſhould joyne with <hi>Hoptons</hi> forces, and the body of the Army to have remained thereabouts till a Fort had been rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon <hi>Kennets</hi> mouth to have ſecured the river, and commanded the towne; but that deſigne was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111861:5"/>not executed, partly becauſe it was then preſt that the moving of the whole Army would better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the City, and would be of greater concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to march toward <hi>Oxford,</hi> to meet with the auxiliary forces of the aſſociated Counties, &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by reaſon of Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> his own Letter, which aſſured my Lord <hi>Generall</hi> that he would preſently obey his commands, and march into the Weſt, which notwithſtanding was not done; for Sir <hi>William</hi> marched to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and went not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Weſt; whereas had they marched thither, they might have been furniſhed with money bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (thoſe Counties being rich and well affected to us) than in judgement could be expected at <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> which was a fortified Garriſon town; nor were Horſe and Dragoones proper or probable to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile againſt it. However Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> not certifying his <hi>Excellence</hi> of the altering his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the reaſons of it, or of his march to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> till after he was engaged in his March, he relyed wholly upon his marching to the Weſt. But by that occaſion necre 20. daies were ſpent ere he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched toward the Weſt, in which time the forces of P. <hi>Maurice,</hi> Marqueſſe <hi>Harford,</hi> and <hi>Hopton</hi> joyned together. The Lord <hi>Generall</hi> (it being much ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as a thing of abſolute neceſſity to move with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111861:5"/>the whole army toward <hi>Oxford,</hi> for pleaſing of the City, from whom otherwiſe we were to expect no money) did, though much againſt judgement, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in that deſigne, and marched to <hi>Thame</hi> with the whole army to meet with the aſſociate forces of the Counties. Upon his comming thither hee found neither his own forces, nor thoſe new forces of that number that was expected and promiſed, there being not above 1000. Dragoons and foot at moſt, which came up to us. At <hi>Thame</hi> the hand of God in an extreme increaſe of ſicknes (hundreds in a day falling deſperately il) and by ſtrong unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of weather, and great raine continuing 14. dayes, the place being upon a flat, clayie, and moiſt ground, made it impoſſible to advance from that quarter. In which time the army was by ſickneſſe, and departure away of moſt of the auxiliary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, brought to a number utterly unable to attempt the former deſign without certaine ruine; the ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of <hi>Oxford</hi> upon the river of <hi>Thames</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it being impoſſible to blocke up the towne without a double number to what his <hi>Excellence</hi> then had. Yet as ſoone as the raine ceaſed, and the waters abated, to make the wayes paſſable, intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence being given that P. <hi>Rupert</hi> had drawn out his horſe &amp; foot toward <hi>Buckingham,</hi> &amp; intended there to give battel, having broght thither, as was reported
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111861:6"/>his Canon, called in the Countrey, and made open profeſſion before them, that upon his honour hee would fight with our forces, though they were 10. for 1. the Lo: <hi>Generall</hi> marched with all ſpeed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Buckingham</hi> to fight with the Enemy, whoſe ſhowes of bravery, and deſires of ſighting quickly came to nothing; for when the Lo: <hi>Generall</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched within two miles of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> intelligence was given that they had all in a diſorderly manner quitted the towne, left their proviſions behinde them, horſt their foot, and were marcht away the night before. His <hi>Excellence</hi> then knowing it was not poſſible for him with his traine of Artillery, and foot to follow the enemy to any advantage, or by thoſe forces he had to hinder P. <hi>Rupert</hi> from joyning with the Queene, deſiſted from his march to <hi>Buckingham,</hi> ſending into the towne a party of horſe to quarter there that night, and to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the enemies proviſion; he himſelfe with the reſt of his Army marched to great <hi>Brickhill,</hi> a place moſt convenient to lye betweene the Enemy and <hi>London,</hi> to defend the aſſociate Counties, to aſſiſt or joyn with the forces of the Lo: <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Grooby,</hi> Sir <hi>John Meldrum,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Crumwel,</hi> to whom his <hi>Excellence</hi> had given many ſtrict commands to have fought with the Queens forces, and ſtopt her paſſage up to the King, for which deſigne they had a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111861:6"/>force; but notwithſtanding it was not done, nor were ſuch opportunities as were offered taken to have fallen upon the enemy; but the Queen and P. <hi>Rupert</hi> were ſuffered to joyn with all their forces. (yet the Lo: <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Grooby</hi> came afterwards readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his forces to his <hi>Excellence.</hi>) About this time came intelligence of good ſucceſſe which Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> had upon the enemy in the Weſt, taken ſome of their Canon, forced them to retreat, and had purſued them to the <hi>Deviſes,</hi> of which his <hi>Excellence</hi> on Tueſday night following the defeat received a Letter from Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> dated on the Monday, confirming the truth of it; which was ſeconded with further intelligence that Sir <hi>W. Wallers</hi> forces had routed more of the Enemies horſe, and beat a convoy of Ammunition ſent from <hi>Oxford</hi> by the Lo: <hi>Craford,</hi> and that the Lo: <hi>Wilmot</hi> upon newes thereof, who was with 2. Regiments of horſe going after the Lo: <hi>Craford,</hi> retreated to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and that the enemy had but 1200. foot left in the Weſterne Counties, which were got into the <hi>Deviſes,</hi> and offered to quit that town upon faire conditions, Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler</hi> having a victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and very conſiderable army before it. Now the caſe ſtanding thus, the feare of the Weſtern parts was changed into joy and thankfulneſs for victory and ſucceſſe, his <hi>Excellence</hi> having out of his great
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111861:7"/>care and circumſpection written to Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler</hi> in theſe words:</p>
            <p>I <hi>Would have you fight with the Marqueſſe of</hi> Hartford, <hi>if poſsibly you may, not upon unequall terms; if not, to march up after him, and to hinder and trouble him in the Reare as much as in you lyes, and ſo joyne with this Army; otherwiſe if the King ſend any ſupply of force to the Enemy there, (if I have notice thereof) I ſhall take all poſsible care to ſupply you accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No information at all was given him of any ſuch forces, nor received he any other Letter from Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> (ſaving one Letter from Sir <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Hazelrick</hi> dated on the Monday at noone, and one other on the Wedneſday, deſiring his <hi>Excellence</hi> to take care of the forces at <hi>Oxford</hi>) during the time that he lay before the <hi>Deviſes,</hi> but ſtill ſuppoſed him to proceed proſperouſly againſt the enemy; untill the ſad news of his being routed was rumo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; by himſelfe written to his <hi>Excellence,</hi> which was upon the Thurſday, not above 48. houres after he received the Letter of his victory (ſcarce time enough to have rid poſte betwixt his <hi>Excellences</hi> army and Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi>) in which Letter Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler</hi> aſſured his <hi>Excellence</hi> he had loſt but 100. men, and ſome armes, which hee doubted not ſuddenly to rally, and reſolved the next day to take the field, not deſiring any aſſiſtance or ſupply from his <hi>Excellence</hi> in either of his Letters. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which, Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> (though
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111861:7"/>the care and ſafety of the Weſtern Countries were committed to him) contrary to his <hi>Excellences</hi> expectation, conſent or knowledge, left the Weſt to take care of it ſelfe, marched to <hi>Warwicke,</hi> and from thence ſent a Letter by an expreſſe to his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence,</hi> ſignifying the imminent danger of the Weſt, eſpecially of <hi>Briſtol</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> unleſſe his <hi>Excellence</hi> did ſpeedily advance, and that he was ready at <hi>Warwick</hi> with his <hi>Might</hi> (his own expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in his Letter) which was affirmed by the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to be 2000.) to aſſiſt him. The Lo: <hi>Generall</hi> preſently upon receit of this intelligence, though there was no money to pay the Souldiers, and the Army then on its march another way, commanded that the Army ſhould march toward the Weſt, and by advice of the Councell of Warre ſent order to Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> to meet tenne miles towards <hi>Brackley,</hi> entending the next day after all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould have met at ſome convenient place of Rendevous, and ſo have proceeded to relieve the Weſt, if it were poſſible, either by falling upon <hi>Oxford,</hi> or marching on to <hi>Briſtol,</hi> as ſhould bee adviſed.</p>
            <p>But Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> before the receipt of his <hi>Excellences</hi> Order was marched to <hi>Northampton,</hi> a contrary way, and ſent Colonell <hi>Popham,</hi> and Col: <hi>Carre</hi> to ſignifie that his force was inconfiderable,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111861:8"/>not above 400. horſe (ſtrangely ſhrunk, if, as is ſaid, he muſtered 2000. at <hi>Briſtol</hi> after his defeat,) that he had a deſire to lay down his Commiſſion, and go to <hi>London.</hi> And the day following he came to his <hi>Excellence,</hi> and aſſured him that his horſe, which was all the ſtrength he had, was ſo inconſiderable, that a Corporal with an ordinary ſquadron of horſe would rout them all, and deſired he might goe to <hi>London,</hi> where he heard there would preſently bee new forces and money raiſed to ſet him out again. This ſtrange newes quaſht the deſign for reliefe of the Weſt, his <hi>Excellences</hi> army being ſhrunk through the continuall encreaſe of violent ſickneſſe, want of pay, cloathing, and other neceſſaries to ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as is not requiſite to name, that he could not proceed further, leſt his army might be engaged to the utter ruine of it, and danger of the Kingdome, ſince Colonell <hi>Crumwels,</hi> and the other forces of thoſe aſſociate Counties were neither willing, nor could with ſafety be commanded ſo far from their own Countries. This notwithſtanding his <hi>Excellence</hi> before <hi>Briſtol</hi> was loſt, offered that if the <hi>Parliament</hi> would ſend him three thouſand foot, and five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horſe to recrewt his army, he would march to relieve it; under which number, conſidering the preſent weakneſſe of his army, he could neither hope to atchieve any thing, nor with ſafety convey
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111861:8"/>his great Artillery. We ſhould extend this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to too great a length, if wee ſhould ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſeverall engagements, which from time to time have been made to him that he ſhould be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with money and other neceſſaries, and the often failings, only that he hath not yet received from the State for his army ſince the beginning 600000. pounds; beſides, at his comming to <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> laſt, the ſouldiers were then promiſed 5. weeks pay, and cloaths; yet after they had ſtayed a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night longer, only a weeks pay was ſent to them at <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> whereupon, there being ſo long before promiſed ſixe weeks, they disbanded to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of above a thouſand, ſaying openly they would be no more fooled with promiſes.</p>
            <p>By what misfortune Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> loſt that ſtrong army, we think it not our part to make any relation; but referre the Reader to what rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his own Commanders will make of it. This briefe narration had no other end than to inform thoſe people in the truth of proceedings, who might through ignorance have been too apt to have thrown undeſerved aſperſions upon our noble <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> and reſtraine thoſe which have already done it, from wronging themſelves any more hereafter: And has extended no farther than the neceſſity of that required; which a judicious Reader will by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111861:9"/>the language eaſily perceive, expreſſing only what impediments have ſometimes croſſed his reall and honourable deſigns, and that without any bitternes of conteſtation, or invectives, conceiving that ſuch things are too much unmanly, and too farre below that pen whoſe ſubject is ſo noble as the vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a man. We will only inſert what we have heard his <hi>Excellence</hi> ſtil profeſſe; that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his true intentions &amp; unwearied en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to ſerve his Countrey have unjuſtly met with ſo many miſunderſtandings (leſſe injuries tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe having made other perſons of quality deſert the cauſe which they had choſen, though ſuch looſe plants could never be well and honourably rooted) it ſhall no whit diſcourage him, much leſſe divert him from that, in which his conſcience to God, &amp; deare affection to his native Country have once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him, but that for the future (hoping that the <hi>Parliament</hi> will afford him juſt and neceſſary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations) his life and fortunes ſhall not be ſpared when the cauſe ſhal require an adventure of them; hoping that God will bleſſe his endeavours and his Country eſteeme of them as they deſerve, ſince Fame, though it be not the chiefe end which a wiſe man ſhoots at in his undertakings, yet it is ſuch a reward as a noble minde cannot eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111861:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
